RG 003, New London County Court African Americans and People of Color Collection
Connecticut State Library
New London County Court African Americans and people of color collection
1701-1854
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. County Court (New London County)
6.5 cubic feet
The New London County Court African Americans and People of Color Collection is an artificial grouping of records consisting of photocopies of cases involving people of color from the Files and Papers by Subject series of the records of New London County Court for the period between 1701 and 1854. All original documents have been retired and second copies have been inserted in the places where the originals were once located.
RG003_NLCC_AA
2004-035
Historical Note
The New London County African Americans and People of Color Collection is an artificial grouping of records consisting of photocopies of cases involving people of color from the Files and Papers by Subject series of the records of New London County Court for the period between 1701 and 1854.1 All original documents have been retired and second copies have been inserted in the places where the originals were once located.
Endnotes
1Records of the New London County Court are divided into four major series - Dockets, Trials, Files, and Papers by Subject. The New London County Court records were transferred to the Connecticut State Library in 1921. For more information on the history of county courts and these records, please see the finding aid for New London County. County Court. Files, 1691-1855.
Research Note
Originally called the African Americans Collection, the title has been modified because many persons found in the collection are identified as Mulatto, black, a person of color, or without any designation whatsoever. It is relatively easy to find court cases concerning or mentioning people of color when some sort of designation like Negro, Indian, Mulatto, black, or colored is used, but such attributions become increasingly rare as the nineteenth century progressed. Both federal census returns and Black Roots in Southeastern Connecticut, 1650-1900 are extremely useful, but often one's decision is based upon the first name or surname or on instinct.95 Naming conventions can be extremely useful in identify people of color. Certain first names like Boston, Bristo, Caesar, Cato, Cuff, Dinah, Jack, Lettice, London, Phillis, Pomp, Prince, and Scipio provide strong indicators that the individuals named are people of color. The situation is similar for such surnames as Brayton, Caples, Condol, Fagins, George, Glasko, Henry, Jacklin, Moody, Orchard, Pelham, Plato, Quash, Quy, Ruggles, Tossett, and Walmsley but many surnames are shared by whites and blacks, like Babcock, Brown, Congdon, Davis, Ellis, Freeman, Hyde, Jackson, Jeffery, Mallison, Mason, Moseley, Peckham, Peters, Rogers, Simons, and Williams. Thus, the task of trying to identify people of color is not an exact science and not doubt errors have been made for both inclusion and exclusion. Still, a collection and accompanying database that contains almost 1,200 records represents a massive new set of data, most of which has not heretofore been examined by researchers.
To cite just two examples of problems that can occur with certain surnames. In the towns of New London and Groton, lived a number of people over a period of 100 years with the surname of Jeffery/Jeffrey. Most were white, but Black Roots identifies several as people of color. Census records do not provide confirmation of that attribution, but the compiler has followed the lead of the authors of Black Roots and has included several Jefferys as people of color.96 The same decision was not made, however, in the case of Benjamin Mallison. Black Roots identified Revolutionary War veteran Benjamin Mallison as a person of color, but probate and Groton vital records clearly indicate that he was white.97
The spelling for names conforms to that found in court cases and sometimes the name of the same person is spelled in different ways in separate cases, for example, Brayton and Briton, Condol and Congdon, and Right and Wright.
Endnotes
95Brown and Rose, Black Roots. The authors compiled data from census, church, justice of the peace, land, pension, probate, town, and vital records, plus account books and some reference to court records.
96Another line of Jeffreys with Niantic Indian blood is identified with the town of Lyme. See Vicki S. Welch, And They Were Related, Too (Xlibris Corporation, 2006).
97Benjamin Mallison was the son of Joseph and Phebe Willcocks Mallison and grandson of Joseph and Elizabeth Mallison.
Scope and Content
The first draft of this finding aid, covering the period 1701-74, contained records of 286 cases involving African Americans and people of color. Subsequent research has increased that number to 298. Another 808 cases involving people of color have been identified for the period between 1781 and 1854 and 85 new records found in Papers by Subject 2. The black population in southeastern Connecticut remained relatively constant from the time of the census of 1774 and the abolition of the county courts in 1855. As slaves gained their freedom, and about 80% were free by 1800, however, they entered into more contracts and became plaintiffs or defendants in more civil and criminal cases.
The person of color is not identified by name, even a first name, in 45 records, 27 from prior to the American Revolution. In 209 other cases, 140 from 1701-74, the people are identified by first name and as a Negro or mulatto, while in around 935 they are identified by first name and surname.3 People of color are defendants or mentioned in 5% of cases prosecuted by the King's Attorney in the colonial era, while the figure jumps to 40% of state prosecutions for the period between 1781 and 1854, a clear reflection of the connection between poverty and lack of opportunity on one hand and crime on the other.4
Genealogists and historians studying people of color in southeastern Connecticut are fortunate to have access to Black Roots in Southeastern Connecticut. This excellent work provides a frame of reference to determine what number and percentage of the cases located in Files and Papers by Subject for the New London County Court can be found in this published work. Of more than 160 named individuals found in New London court records for the colonial era, about 38% are represented in Black Roots. In total, this project identified more than 1,400 people of color, a figure that includes Native Americans, almost 55% (788) are listed in Black Roots and the remaining 658 are not.
Prior to the American Revolution, only a relatively small minority of African Americans was free, but this small group of individuals made up a significant percentage of cases. The records contain 29 lawsuits involving Robert Jacklin, around 45 on the Jackson family of New London, 25 on members of the Wright family (1710-74), and 21 on the Rogers family of New London (1720-49).5 For the post-Revolutionary War period, half a dozen persons appear with great frequency. Isaac C. Glasko of Griswold is represented in 15 lawsuits (1811-49),6 Prince Brown of Lyme in named in 13 (1814-35), mostly regarding references to his land holdings, Benjamin Beach of Norwich in 11 (1820-38), Caesar Beckwith of Lyme in 7 (1800-09), Pero Moody of Preston and Lisbon 7 (1786-1823), and Peggy Sansom of New London in 7 (1831-50)
Robert Jacklin of New London, Colchester, and Norwalk came to New London from Newbury, Mass. in 1711 after he was emancipated.7 Jacklin was the cause of a 1717 unsuccessful petition to the General Assembly from the inhabitants of New London urging it to pass legislation prohibiting free Negroes from owning land.8 He was the plaintiff in six cases and defendant in twenty-three others. He owned and rented land in both New London and Colchester but had difficulty in paying his bills, as all the cases in which he was a defendant demonstrate. In 1732, George Holmes of Colchester sued Samuel Atwell to collect a debt owed to Jacklin. In 1729 as he was about to remove to Norwalk, Jacklin had given Holmes his power of attorney to collect monies owed him.9 Descendants of Robert Jacklin appear in the records of the Litchfield County Court.
The collection includes around forty-five cases concerning John Jackson, his wife Joan, and their children.10 Although John Jackson was free, Joan was not, and the New London County Court dealt with a whole series of cases over a period of some fifty years in which the court attempted to determine who was and was not free. In the first lawsuit concerning Joan, James Rogers, Junr. v. Samuel Beebe in 1710, the plaintiff claimed that Joan of right belonged to him, while the defendant who was married to the sister of Rogers argued that Joan belonged to him, "by Virtue of an Order obtained from Mrs. Elizabeth Rogers Relick of Mr. James Rogers deceased... to Deliver sd. Joan to him the Defendant."11 Another case occurred in June 1711, Samuel Beebe v. John Rogers & John Jackson. According to the writ, Rogers and Jackson sailed from New London for Southold, Long Island, where, according to the plaintiff, they "had Stollen out his house at long Iland, a Negro woman Named Joan, and her two Negro Children."12
Hagar Wright, often spelled Right, was freed in around 1691 and is represented in six lawsuits, while her children and grandchildren appear in another nineteen.13 Most are relatively straightforward debt cases, but two concerned attempts by James Rogers to re-enslave Hagar and one of her children. In the first case, James Rogers, Jr. sued his uncle John Rogers, Sr., founder of the Rogerenes, for ownership of the fourteen-year old son of Hagar.14 In the second case, Hagar [Wright] v. James Rogers, she sued to confirm that she and all her children were "free from Servitude." Documentation includes a petition from Hagar in which she stated that although she and her children had been freed, but "being a poor & dispised widow woman" through "ignorance" had not proven it before the county court at the requisite time in 1710. She asked the court to confirm that she and her children were free.15 In a later case, Waitt Right v. Sarah Prentice, Wright, a son of Hagar, stated that he had served on board the sloop Defence under the command of Capt. John Prentice, deceased, in the 1745 expedition to Cape Breton that culminated in the capture of Louisburg. The plaintiff claimed that the crew numbered 101 that he was never paid his share of £5,00016 in prize money and sued for his "Just Part or Right in sd 5000 With his Just Damage and Coast."17
Adam Rogers was a mulatto from New London who married a white woman, Catherine Jones.18 He was plaintiff or defendant in thirteen cases between 1720 and 1747 and sons Adam, Jr. and John are represented by eight more cases from 1732 to 1739. Rogers is classified as a mulatto in New London church records, but his race is mentioned in just two 1720 court cases. He acquired some land after the death of his father-in-law Thomas Jones and was the plaintiff in seven of the thirteen cases in which he appears. In November 1744, May 1745, and June 1747, Rogers sued Joseph Bolles of New London for trespass. He stated that "on the 28th of June Last past and for 30 years before he was in actuall possession of a mention [mansion] house and farme" and that the defendant "with force and Arms in a violent manner... turned ye plantiffs wife and Daughter out of said House and also ye plantiffs household Stuff."19 All three lawsuits were eventually withdrawn.
For the post-Revolutionary era, court records also contain material that can helpful in writing biographies of people of color, as, for example, Pero Moody (1750-1830) and Isaac C. Glasko (d. 1861), two men of some importance in the struggle of Connecticut African Americans to obtain equal rights. In 1823, Moody and Glasko unsuccessfully petitioned the General Assembly for exemption from taxation on the grounds that they were denied the right to vote.20 Court records provide a great deal of new information about these two previously little known men. Pero Moody is found in seven court cases between 1783 and 1823, while Glasko was a party in fifteen from 1811 to 1849, mostly ordinary debt cases. Moody on the other hand had a much more interesting legal history. In November 1783, for example, William Mattison of Preston, who had supposedly freed Moody six years earlier, sued Nathaniel Cogswell for illegally purchasing goods and provisions from his "Negro man Servant named Pero."21 Two and one half years later Cogswell sued Pero and his brother Tidal Moody for £20 damages, claiming that one "Mindo A Slave to them (meaning Pero and Tidal) for life" had come to the plaintiff's house in a "Suffering Condition" and that he had spent over £17 caring for him. The Moodys hired lawyers to defend them and the attorneys argued that Pero and Tidal could not be sued because Pero was "a slave for Life" and, therefore, by law "Cannot make any Contrac[c] that is binding."22 Moody appears again in December 1788 case involving the care of Lucretia Stanton, a poor inhabitant of Groton who fell sick on a trip to Preston and died in that town. Moody nursed her for more than six weeks and paid the costs for a sheet to cover her body, a coffin, and digging the grave. He received £5-4 reimbursement.23 The last case involving Moody was heard by the March 1823 session of the county court. He sued Russel Rose and William Waters, assessors for the Town of Lisbon, in a plea of trespass, claiming that on October 20, 1819 one year after the adoption of the Constitution of 1818 that, "the plaintiff then being in said Town of Lisbon but not having although guiltless of every crime, the privileges of a Citizen and inhabitant of Said State nor the right of suffrage therein, and not being liable to a poll or other tax in Said State... Russel and William under colour and pretence of Law... made out a List of the plaintiff['s] estate." Moody had been assessed $2.10 in town taxes, had refused to pay, had a wagon attached for non-payment of taxes, and was forced to pay them for its return. The case was initially tried before a local justice of the peace in August 1822 who rendered judgment in favor of Moody. The defendants appealed to the county court and it overturned the original judgment.24 This lawsuit served as the basis for the subsequent petition to the General Assembly.
In other instances, court records provide context and information on individuals briefly mentioned in other sources. An article on "Letters by African American Sailors, 1799-1804" published in the January 2007 issue of the William and Mary Quarterly, for example, one Isaac Rogers of New London is mentioned.25 Court records tell us that two Isaac Rogers lived in New London at the beginning of the 19th century. The court distinguished the two by identifying the Isaac of color as, "Isaac Rogers Alias Black Isaac."26 The Isaac Rogers of color appeared in six cases between 1799 and 1823.
The first case involving African Americans dates from September 1701 when John Jackson, the Negro servant of John Rogers of New London, was accused by Catherine Jones, a white woman, of fathering her bastard child by fornication. Jones was fined and whipped, while Jackson was required to pay for the maintenance of the mulatto child for four years.27 The second case, John Rayner v. Edward DeWolfe, took place three years later. Rayner accused Mingo, the Negro servant of DeWolfe, of threatening to kill him. Twenty-seven men from Lyme signed a petition attesting to Mingo's good character, saying that "wee do nott Know of any Wronge that hee hath Dun to any person... Since hee Came to This Town."28
A number of subjects are covered in these African American cases. For the period between 1701 and 1774, the collection contains 96 suits for debt, 22 for attachment, 19 disputes over ownership, 17 cases of trespass, and 16 of fraudulent sale. It also includes 8 writs of execution, 7 cases of theft, 7 disputes over sale of slaves, and 7 of assault and battery. Other subjects include arson, cruelty, fornication, suits for freedom, lascivious carriage, nonpayment for services, runaways, and those in which Negro witnesses appeared. Similar subjects find representation in the years 1781-1854, except that lawsuits concerning slave owning and runaways end by 1800.
Almost exactly one third of all cases concerned debt, a figure that holds constant for both the pre and post-Revolutionary periods. The plaintiff and/or the defendant were free in all these cases. In a handful debt cases, both the plaintiff and defendant were African Americans.29 The first case in which a free Negro sued a white man is Adam Rogers "Molatto" v. Thomas Williams. The plaintiff sued for twenty-two shillings in a debt by book and recovered judgment for the entire sum in June 1720.30 The February 1731 court heard the case of Samuel Doty v. Samuel Wright, "a Malotto Man of Lyme," in which the plaintiff sued to collect £3-15 that Wright owed by book. The defendant confessed judgment and the plaintiff collected £3 debt and £1 costs.31 More typical is a series of three February 1753 cases involving Hector, alias Hector Throope, formerly of Lebanon but then of New London; Ichabod Robinson v. Hector "a free Negro Man," Jonathan Trumble v. Hector, and Nehemiah Waterman v. Hector. The defendant owed some £150 in depreciated old tenor currency. He confessed judgment in all three cases, but was unable to pay his debts. John Alden paid the three judgments and court costs and in return the court assigned Hector to the service of Alden for seven years.32
The records contain more than 270 debt lawsuits for the post-Revolutionary War period, in the majority of which the person of color was the defendant, as for example in December 1813 when Japhet Harmon and Jack A[l]my were successfully sued for debt.33 Two additional cases were tried in November 1835, the first involving two people of color and the second in which the defendant was "a coloured man."34 Isaac C. Glasko of Griswold forms major exception to the rule that most African Americans were defendants in debt cases. He was plaintiff in seven and defendant in six debt cases.
Enslaved African Americans were considered property and they could be attached along with other real and personal property to ensure that a defendant would appear before the county court to answer the charges brought against him. Files for the period between 1701 and 1774 contain twenty-two cases in which slave property was attached by a constable or deputy sheriff. The first such case took place in February 1740 in Timothy Mather v. Thomas Peck. The defendant from Stratford had purchased in December 1736 a writ in favor of Thomas Bohanning of New York City against Thomas Clements of Lyme for £22. The plaintiff, a constable from Lyme, had served the writ on Clements, had attached a Negro man belonging to Clements, and boarded him for eight months while the action was pending. Mather, however, had not been compensated for his services and sued for £27 damages. The court found for the plaintiff but the defendant appealed to the Superior Court.35 In 1763, a "Negrow Boy Named Bristow about 8 years old" was attached in six different cases in which the defendant was Samuel Hull of Norwich.36 The last slave attachment in the colonial era occurred in June 1774 in the case of Samuel Whittelsey v. John Kirtland in a debt by book for £30. As surety, constable Andrew Lord of Saybrook attached "one Negro Girl Named Phillis about two or three Year old" and "one Negro Woman About twenty Years Old Namd Tamar."37
A second form of attachment was by writ of execution. After a defendant had been convicted and fined, property was seized by writ of execution and sold at auction if he could not pay the debt. The collection contains eight such cases. In Gilbert Fanning v. Joseph Denison & John Williams 4th, constable Fanning had served a writ of execution on August 19, 1774 directed against John Williams Esq. of Stonington for £91-19-6. He attached two yoke of oxen, "one negro Boy about twelve years of Age named Quash," and a "Stone horse" or stallion. All were temporarily turned over to the defendants on the promise that they would deliver them to the signpost in Stonington on September 8 for sale. The defendants failed to do so, defaulted, and were ordered to pay the plaintiff £115 debt and £1-6-3 court costs.38
The records contain a number of disputes over ownership of slaves. One representative case is that of Charles Bulkley v. John Richards. The plaintiff served as administrator of the estate of Benjamin Swetland of New London, deceased, who in his lifetime possess clothes, household goods, tools, fabrics, "one Negro man Slave for Life Mingo £50," and "one Negro Woman Slave for Life Rose £25." All the listed items had come into the hands of the defendant who had refused to return them to the administrator of the estate. The court found for the plaintiff and the defendant appealed to the Superior Court.39 In another case, Joseph Hunt of Westchester, New York sued Jonathan Haines of New London over the ownership of Ceasar. The plaintiff had purchased Ceasar from Jonathan Rogers and claimed that the defendant, although knowing of Hunt's purchase, took a mortgage from Rogers "of said Negro." The jury found for the plaintiff and the defendant appealed.40
Cases involving fraudulent sale almost invariably revolved around the health of the slave being purchased. In fifteen of sixteen fraudulent sale lawsuits, the plaintiff charged the defendant with falsely claiming that the slave purchased was of sound body. In the June 1735 case of John Pike v. James Otis, the plaintiff stated that in May 1732 he purchased "a Negro Woman slave Called fillis" for £31 and the defendant warranted that she was "Good, healthy, and well." Pike discovered, however, that Fillis was blind and he sued to recover his purchase price.41 Jonathan Harris sued Peter Brown over the sale of a Negro youth James about seventeen years old. The defendant asserted that James was in good health and that although he was well worth £500 in depreciated old tenor, he could be purchased for £160. The plaintiff "bought the Said Negro depending and relying upon the Decl[aratio]n of the D[efendant]t aforsaid, Yet... the Said Negro Was Subject to fitts which Render him altogether unfit for any Sort of Business & wholly deprived him of his Natural Reason." He asked for £500 damages, but the case was withdrawn.42 The only case that did not concern health, Mathew McCure v. Samuel Tyler, both of Killingworth, the mulatto girl in question was determined to have been free born.43
Disputes over the sale of slaves, specifically for nonpayment, are similar in character but not identical to lawsuits over fraudulent contract. Typical of such cases is Peter Buor v. Benjamin Ellard that concerned the sale of two Negro men, Thomas and Quamino, for £300. The defendant neglected to pay the agreed sum, the court found in favor of the plaintiff, and the defendant appealed.44 Another eleven cases revolved around the subject of enticing slaves to depart from the service of their master, seven from before the American Revolution and four thereafter. At the November 1737 court, Nathaniel Backus, Jr. of Norwich accused Jedidiah Frink of Voluntown of enticing his servant Primas away. The jury, however, did not agree and acquitted the defendant. Backus appealed.45